Finding Aid for Woodruff-Marin Family Papers 1891-1950s
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Woodruff-Marin Family Papers 1891-1950s, 1891-1896, 1939-1950
Woodruff Family Papers
1 oversize folder
1 linear foot
The Woodruffs were a lumbering family from Ludington, Michigan. The collection includes clippings, correspondence and photographs. The Woodruff family materials contain photo books and prints of the University of Michigan area during the 1890s, and correspondence home to the family from U-M students. The Marin family materials include information on Axel Marin's career as a University of Michigan professor, and photographs of Michigan football, ca. 1940.
0186 Aa 2 UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Edwin W. and Jane A. Marin (donor no. 9063 ) in February 2001.
The collection is open for research.
John F. Woodruff (1841-1917) was a Michigan Lumberman based in St. Clair and Ludington, Michigan. He was married to Helen F. Williams, daughter of Jeremiah D. Williams of Ann Arbor, the Republican State representative for Washtenaw County. Their sons, Eugene C. Woodruff (1871-1944) and Edwin F. Woodruff (1874-1898) attended the University of Michigan in the early 1890s with Edwin F. Woodruff received his BS in engineering in 1896.
Eugene C. Woodruff received a BS in engineering in 1894, a MS in music in 1896, and a PhD in engineering in 1900. His work was on electrical engineering, in particular automatic push-button controls for electric trolley cars and the creation of electricity. Eugene Woodruff taught at the high school level between his degrees. After his PhD he taught at several universities, including Montana State University, Milliken University in Illinois, and Penn State University. While teaching, he continued to research electrical transportation, as well as radio and automobile electrical systems. In 1900, Eugene Woodruff married Goyce Houston of Vassar, Michigan, the daughter of State Senator Benjamin W. Houston. Their daughter, Helen Woodruff, also attended the University of Michigan, receiving her BA in 1923. Helen Woodruff then became a professor and the Dean of Women at Flint City College, teaching French and Spanish.
Victor Marin (b. 1865) immigrated to the United States from Stockholm, Sweden in 1886 to join his father, a fine building finisher, in Manistique, Michigan. In 1888, Victor Marin was able to send for his sweetheart, Mathilda C. Humble, and they were married the same year. The couple had twelve sons, and nine of them finished high school in Manistique. Axel Marin (1896-1980) went on to the University of Michigan, graduating with a BS in mechanical engineering in 1922, and began teaching mechanical engineering at the university. Axel Marin married Lois A. Fischer, daughter of John C. Fischer (1886-1934), owner of Ann Arbor's Fischer Hardware. In 1922 Axel Marin became president of Fischer Hardware while continuing to teach at the University. Axel Marin also served on the University of Michigan Board of Intercollegiate Athletics in the 1940's. Fred Marin also graduated from the University of Michigan in 1924 with a degree in business, and began a career as a state banks examiner.
Fred Marin married Helen Woodruff in 1926. Their son, Edwin W. Marin, and his wife, Jane A. Marin are the donors of this collection.
The Woodruff-Marin papers contain information about Ann Arbor, the University of Michigan, and greater Michigan. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs taken by Eugene C. Woodruff between 1890 and 1896. The collection is arranged into two series, the Woodruff Family Papers and the Marin Family Papers.
Subjects:
Woodruff family.; Marin family.; University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; University of Michigan--Student letters.; Woodruff, Edwin F.; Woodruff, Eugene Cyrus, 1871-1944
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Business enterprises--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Circus parades--Michigan--Petoskey.; Fischer Hardware (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Hardware stores--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ludington (Mich.); Lumber industry--Michigan.; Marin family.; Saint Clair (Mich.); University of Michigan. College of Engineering--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Football.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1950.; Waterman Gymnasium (University of Michigan); Woodruff family.
Contributors:
Woodruff, Edwin F.; Woodruff, Eugene Cyrus, 1871-1944
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Woodruff Family Papers
  The Woodruff Family Papers consists of two subseries: Clippings and Correspondence and Photographs.
  - Correspondence and Clippings
    The Clippings and Correspondence subseries includes biographical clippings and a family tree, as well as correspondence between Eugene C. Woodruff and his brother Edwin F. Woodruff to their parents, John S. Woodruff and Helen F. Williams, in Ludington, Michigan while they attended the University of Michigan in the early 1890s.
    - Biographical materials, clippings 1899-1944 (Box 1)
    - Eugene C. and Edwin F. Woodruff correspondence with family 1892-1896 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    The Photographs subseries contains portraits of Eugene C. Woodruff, Edwin F. Woodruff, and Eugene's wife, Goyce Houston Woodruff, as well as images of the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor and the surrounding area. Many of the photographs were taken by Eugene C. Woodruff and bound with string into photograph books, although there are some individual prints. The University of Michigan images include campus buildings, student life, and student athletics. Included are photographs of the family home in Ludington, the family summer home in Bay View, and visits to St. Clair and the Upper Peninsula. The photographs also contain images of logging operations, Eugene C. Woodruff's electrical engineering experiments, and copies of family portraits.
    - Portraits
      - Eugene C. Woodruff circa 1890s, 1930s (Box 1)
      - Edwin F. Woodruff circa 1895 (Box 1)
        (See also Bay View and St. Clair Photograph Book for family member's portrait copies)
      - Goyce Houston Woodruff portraits and photographs circa 1900 (Box 1)
    - Photograph Books
      - University of Michigan
        - Student and fraternity life, student antics, student trips to Whitmore Lake and Webster Township, MI, bicycle repair 1891-1893 (Box 1)
        - Storm damage, Huron River, Winter 1892-1893 (Box 1)
        - Campus buildings, Waterman Gym construction, "Co-Ed Annex" barn 1892-1893 (Box 1)
        - Student life, athletics: baseball, fencing, football circa 1893 (Box 1)
        - Student quarters 1896; Senior's football team (includes Edwin F. Woodruff); Eugene C. Woodruff's thesis experiment; Woodruff Brothers portraits circa 1895 (Box 1)
      - Michigan
        - Bayview and St. Clair, MI, family Vacation, family portrait copies, Eugene Woodruff's electrical experiments circa 1892 (Box 1)
        - Ludington, MI, family photos, Ludington homes, staged scene photos, winter 1891-1892 (Box 1)
        - St. Clair, MI, vacation, family photos, Solis family 1892-1893 (Box 1)
        - Upper Peninsula, family on the "E.P. Weed" boat, boats, snowplow circa 1892 (Box 1)
    - Photographs
      - University of Michigan
        - Woodruff Brothers student living quarters circa 1892 (Box 1)
        - 1896 Senior's football team photographs circa 1895-1896 (Folder UAm)
        - Student club photographs including Eugene C. Woodruff 1891-1894 (Box 1)
        - School of Music circa 1895 (Box 1)
        - Scientific experiments circa 1900 (Box 1)
      - Michigan
        - Au Sable River fishing trip circa 1892 (Box 1)
        - Logging photographs, likely near Ludington circa 1880s (Box 1)
        - Ludington, MI, family home, harbor circa 1982 (Box 1)
        - Ludington, MI, girl in tent 1906 (Folder UAm)
        - Petoskey, MI, circus parade circa 1892 (Box 1)
        - St. Clair, MI, Congregational Church circa 1892 (Box 1)
- Marin Family Papers
  The Marin Family Papers mainly concern Axel Marin, a University of Michigan mechanical engineering graduate in 1922 who continued to teach engineering at the University. Axel Marin was a member of the University of Michigan Board in Control of Intercollegiate Athletics and the collection includes materials about University of Michigan football during the 1940's. There are photographs of Axel Marin and his wife, Lois A. Fischer, and limited information on her family's Fischer Hardware Store in Ann Arbor. The papers also contain oversize class photographs that include Fred Marin, who graduated from the University of Michigan with a business degree in 1924.
  - Clippings and Printed Materials
    - Biographical clippings 1930-1932 (Box 1)
    - Brochure for football reunion 1939 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Fred Marin University of Michigan Class photographs circa 1924 (Folder UAm)
    - Axel Marin, University of Michigan Professor of Engineering, and his wife, Lois (Fischer) circa 1950 (Box 1)
    - Fischer Hardware, photograph and deed 1950 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan football field circa 1940 (Box 1)
    - University of Michigan football player portraits circa 1940s (Box 1)
    - Michigan postcards circa 1925 (Box 1)
    - Unidentified sorority photograph 1911 (Box 1)